jet2holidays.com 2019-03-31

# Privacy policy | Jet2holidays

#### About this policy

At **_Jet2.com_** and **_Jet2holidays_** , we are committed to only collecting, using and disclosing your personal data in ways that you expect and have consented to or as we are required or permitted to by law. This policy explains how we use your information and applies to all **_Jet2.com_** and **_Jet2holidays_** customers and visitors to our apps and our websites (together our “websites”).

We understand that not everybody needs or wants to know how we use their information in the same level of detail, so we have created two levels of information for you.  If you just want to know the basics, please read the 'essential information' section for each topic.  If you want to know more, please read the ‘detailed information’ section so that you can learn more about a particular issue. 

#### Who is the controller of your data?

#### What personal data do we process?

**Essential Information**

#### Where does your personal data come from?

#### Do you have to provide your personal data?

#### What do we use your personal data for?

  * _for marketing purposes_ : We (including our group companies and partners) and carefully selected third parties may use your personal data to inform you, by email, letter, phone or SMS, about offers, products and services that we think may be of interest to you and we may tell you about other organisations' products and services. We will tell you about this when we collect your information and if you do not wish to receive these communications, please let us know. You can change your mind at any time by visiting our unsubscribe page here https://www.jet2holidays.com/unsubscribe or https://www.jet2.com/unsubscribe or by contacting us at _privacy@jet2.com_. You can also unsubscribe following the instructions that we will include in any communication, such as email or text, we send to you;
  * _for marketing purposes with social media_ : We may use your personal data to generate targeted marketing on various social media sites, for example but not limited to, Facebook. If you do not wish to receive such targeted marketing generally, you are able to switch this off within the social media site. If you do not want to receive such targeted marketing from us, you can contact us at: [privacy@jet2.com](mailto:privacy@jet2.com);
  * to _respond to and deal with any complaint or query or request_ which you contact us with.  As part of our customer care procedures, we may also follow-up, either by letter, phone, SMS, email, or via social media, with customers who have travelled with us, for example to resolve a complaint or to ask for a testimonial;
  * to _comply with your requests to exercise your rights under data protection legislation_ such as when you request access to your personal data;
  * to _administer promotions and competitions_ which we run from time to time;
  * for _market research_ : from time to time, we may also use your information to contact you by letter, phone, SMS or email to conduct customer satisfaction surveys or similar market research exercises;
  * for the purposes of ensuring _safety and security_ on our flights and in our resorts;
  * to _help us design our websites and improve your experience_ : we may collect information about the way you use and access our websites. Our web system collects information about each visitor, including IP address, the length of time spent on the website and the order in which pages are visited. Our web site may use technologies to help analyse how users navigate our web pages, links and forms. This is explained in more detail in the cookies section [here](https://www.jet2holidays.com/cookies)
  * for _fraud prevention_ : to protect our customers and us from fraud and theft, we may look at information that we get from identity checks along with information in our customer records and other information which is publically available (including on social media); 
  * for meeting our _regulatory obligations_ , including liaising with regulatory authorities and for our own internal audit purposes;
  * for _complying with applicable laws and regulations_ ;
  * for _training and quality purposes_ to make sure we continue to deliver the standard of service that you expect from us;
  * to _comply with lawful requests_ by public authorities, discovery requests, or where otherwise required or permitted by applicable laws, court orders, government regulations, or regulatory authorities; 
  * _to enforce our legal rights and obligations_ and for any purposes in connection with any legal claims made by or involving you including reviewing information which you have made publically available and which may be relevant to any claim (including information available on social media sites); and
  * for planning, due diligence and implementation in relation to _a commercial transaction or service transfer_ that affects customers, for example mergers and acquisitions or a sale of all or part of our business. 

#### What are the legal grounds for processing your personal data?

  * the processing is necessary to perform a contract with you (i.e. the contract for the sale and purchase of your flight or holiday), or to take steps requested by you before entering into this contract;
  * the processing is in our or someone else's legitimate interests, and these interests are not overridden by your interests or rights in the protection of your personal data;
  * you have given your consent to the processing of your data; or
  * the processing is necessary to meet a legal obligation which applies to us.

Sometimes we process data about you which the law considers to fall within special categories (see section "What personal data do we process?" for more details), in which case, we use one of the following grounds:

  * the processing is necessary to protect your vital interests or those of another person where you are physically or legally incapable of giving consent (e.g. in the event of a medical emergency);
  * the processing is necessary for the establishment, exercise or defence of legal claims;
  * the processing is necessary for reasons of substantial public interest on the basis of EU or domestic law; or
  * you have freely given your consent to the processing. 

Please see the table below if you want to know which particular grounds we use for each particular processing activity.

**Detailed Information**

**** We explain below which particular ground we use for each activity.  Where we rely on the ground that the processing is in our or someone else's legitimate interests, we explain what those interests are (data protection laws require us to tell you about this).

Type of data/ processing activity | Ground relied on | Ground relied on for special category data | Details about the legitimate interest where this ground relied upon  
---|---|---|---  
  
Compliance with a legal obligation

| 

Perform-ance of a contract

| 

Jet2.com's/ Jet2holidays legitimate interests

| Consent  
To make bookings for flights or holidays. | - |  | - | - | N/A | N/A  
  
To amend bookings and answer queries relating to existing bookings.

| - |  | - | - | N/A | N/A  
  
Payment data gathered in the course of making and receiving payments.

| - |  | - | - | N/A | N/A  
Marketing of flights and holidays to our customers. | - | - |  | - | N/A | 

To market flights and holidays to customers who have a relationship with Jet2.com or Jet2holidays and are likely to be interested in hearing about future offers.  
  
Emails and SMS messages providing updates relating to flight and holiday details.

| - | - |  | - | N/A | To provide flight and holiday updates to customers relating to their bookings.  
Answering customer complaints and queries. | - | - |  | - | 

Specific consent where special category data is provided as part of a query / complaint.

| To investigate and respond to complaints and queries about our products and services.  
To conduct satisfaction surveys with customers. | - | - |  | - | N/A | To allow Jet2.com and Jet2holidays to improve the quality of the products and services which it provides to customers.  
To manage safety of customers and report safety incidents. |  | - | - | - | Necessary for reasons of substantial public interest. | To ensure safety of customers and to manage aircraft and resort safety.  
Printing and posting travel tickets to customers | - |  | - | - | N/A | N/A  
Managing boarding and departures of aircraft. | - |  | - | - | N/A | N/A  
To log incidents of disruptive passengers. | - | - |  | - | N/A | To comply with our responsibility to ensure safety of flights and inform any potential sanction decisions.  
Manging sales made within airports (e.g. excess baggage). | - |  | - | - | N/A | N/A  
To locate lost baggage. | - |  | - | - | N/A | N/A  
Tailoring Jet2.com and Jet2holidays website content to customers. | - | - |  | - | N/A | To assist Jet2.com and Jet2holidays in designing their website and improving the customer experience.  
  
Selling excursions to Jet2.com and Jet2holidays customers before departure or in resort.

| - |  | - | - | N/A | N/A  
Management of any customer health and safety issues. | - | - |  | - | Specific consent where required. | To manage and record passenger medical issues.  
For training and quality purposes. | - | - |  | - | N/A | Processing of customer data as part of our ongoing training programme for our team.  
Detection and prevention of fraud. | - | - |  | - | N/A | To protect Jet2.com and Jet2holidays and its customers against fraudulent activity  
  
To manage payment of compensation under The Flight Compensation Regulation 261/2004.

|  | - | - | - | N/A |   
To respond to Subject Access Requests. |  | - | - | - | Specific consent as required to process Subject Access Requests | N/A  
  
To assess and defend claims made against Jet2.com and Jet2holidays

| - | - |  | - | As necessary to defend claim. | To investigate and manage legal claims.  
To assist law enforcement bodies with their functions. | - | - |  | - | N/A | To comply with lawful requests by law enforcement bodies.  
  
In the course of doing so we may sometimes transfer data outside of the UK and when we do so we make sure that it is protected to the same standards as in the UK.

In relation to passengers making reservations to destinations in the United States of America we are required to transfer to the US Department of Homeland Security ( **"DHS"** ) certain travel and reservation data about passengers flying between the European Union and the United States of America in accordance with an International Agreement between the European Union and the United States. 

US authorities use this information for preventing and combating terrorism and other transnational serious crimes. For further information about the way in which the DHS uses this data please see : [www.dhs.gov](http://www.dhs.gov/) and this [PDF](https://www.dhs.gov/xlibrary/assets/privacy/privacy_faq_pnr_cbp.pdf). Depending on the country you are travelling to we may also be required to share your information with other border agencies. 

**Detailed Information**

**** The types of third party service providers who we share your data with include companies which help us understand our customer behaviour or help improve our website, local airports and third party ground handlers who help provide services to you and our local partners in relation to package holidays.  We always have contracts in place with these third parties which require them to properly protect your data and only use it for the purposes of providing the particular service.

Where hotels which you stay in make decisions themselves about how to use your personal data they will be the data controller of that information and we would encourage you to read their privacy policy to understand how they handle your information and how to exercise your rights.

As part of providing your holiday we will engage local operators (for example, to arrange airport transfers) and we will share your personal data with them so they we can make sure your holiday runs smoothly.

If we sell or buy any business or assets, we will disclose your personal data to the prospective seller or buyer of such business or assets, and if we or part of our business is acquired by a third party, personal data about our customers will be transferred to that third party.

In the event of medical emergency during a flight we may share personal data with third party service providers to call for advice for the purposes of managing and recording passenger medical issues. Your personal data may also be included in a flight report which is sent to the flight operator. 

If you purchase car hire through _**Jet2holidays**_ we will transfer your personal data to Rental Cars (Travel Jigsaw Limited) to provide you with car hire services. **_Jet2holidays_** and Rental Cars will be independent data controllers in respect of that information. Rental Cars will use the information in accordance with their privacy policy <https://www.jet2carhire.com/PrivacyPolicy.do>

We also share personal data for the purposes of fraud prevention and detection with other group companies and other organisations (including law enforcement agencies) involved in fraud prevention and detection. This includes sharing your details with a third party fraud management solution providers, in order to identify potentially fraudulent bookings.

If there are any incidents with disruptive passengers on board our flights, we may share personal data with law enforcement agencies. We also share personal data relating to reported incidents, complaints and feedback in relation to **_Jet2holidays_** with our travel partners and local agents.

In order to assess and defend any legal claims made against us, we may share your personal data with our legal advisors and claims handlers. We may also share your information with law enforcement and government agencies where this is reasonable for the prevention and detection of crime or if we believe a claim is being made fraudulently.

We also pass your information to border agencies where this is required to travel to certain countries.

#### How long do we keep your personal data for?

We will store your personal information for as long as is reasonably necessary for the purposes for which it was collected, as explained in this Privacy Policy. In some cases we may store your personal information for longer periods of time where we need to maintain an accurate record of your dealings with us to help manage complaints or claims you or others may raise, or otherwise comply with legal or regulatory requirements. If you would like to know more about how long we retain information please contact us.

#### What are your rights?

You have several rights in relation to your personal data. These include accessing your data, correcting any mistakes, having your data erased, restricting the processing of your data, objecting to the processing of your data, data portability, and rights relating to automated decision making and profiling. In most cases there are conditions attached to these rights. Please see the relevant sections below if you want to find out more. 

To exercise your rights please contact our Data Protection Officer at _:_ [privacy@jet2.com](mailto:privacy@jet2.com) or, to make a request to access your data, follow the instructions below.

**Detailed Information**

****Accessing your data****

You can ask us to confirm whether we are processing your personal data and to give you a copy of that data along with further information about how we use your personal data.

******** To make a request to access your data please send us your request in writing, signed and dated to the address below along with:

  * your full name and address; ****
  * **** a photocopy of your passport or driving licence, so that we can verify your identity; and
  * details of the personal data you require (along with any further details which may help us to identify you, such as dates and times of flights, destination and booking reference number if you know this). ****

If you are requesting a copy of personal data on behalf of a third party, please also send to us a signed authority from the individual whose data is required and a copy of their passport or driving licence. If the third party is a child under the age of 16, the written authority should come from a person with parental responsibility (along with a copy of the child’s passport). 

Please send your request to: Data Protection Department, Legal Services, Jet2.com Limited, PO Box 284, Leeds, LS11 1GE or electronically to: [privacy@jet2.com](mailto:privacy@jet2.com).

You do not have to pay a fee for a copy of your information unless your request is unfounded, repetitive or excessive, in which case we will charge a reasonable amount in the circumstances.  We will let you know of any charges before completing your request.

**** We aim to respond to you within 1 month of receiving your request unless it is particularly complicated or you have made several requests, in which case we aim to respond within 3 months.  We will let you know if we are going to take longer than 1 month in dealing with your request.  If we have a lot of information about you we might ask you if you can tell us what exactly you want to receive.  This will help us action your request more quickly.

**Correcting your data**

You can ask us to correct any data which is inaccurate or incomplete.  This is free of charge.

We aim to deal with requests for correction within 1 month, although it might take us up to 3 months if your request is particularly complicated.

If we can't action a request to correct your data, we will let you know and explain why this is. 

**Erasing your data**

This right is sometimes referred to as "the right to be forgotten".  This is not an absolute right but you have the right to have your data erased, free of charge, in certain circumstances. 

There are some exceptions to this right.  If one of these applies, we will confirm this to you and we do not have to delete the data.

**Restricting the processing of your data**

You can ask us to restrict the processing of your personal data in some circumstances, free of charge.  This is not an absolute right.  If processing is restricted we can store the data and retain enough information to make sure the restriction is respected, but we cannot further process your data.

We will tell you if we decide to lift a restriction on processing your data. ****

**Objecting to the processing of your data**

Objecting to the processing of your data is free of charge.  It is not an absolute right but you can object to our processing of your data where it is:

  * based on the legitimate interests ground; or
  * for the purposes of scientific/historical research and statistics.

We will stop processing your personal data unless we have compelling legitimate grounds for the processing which override your interests and rights, or unless we are processing the data for the establishment, exercise or defence of legal claims.

**** You can require us to stop using your data for direct marketing purposes.  We will process your request as soon as it is received but it may take up to 14 days for this to be effective.  There are no exemptions or reasons for us to refuse.

**Data Portability**

This allows you to obtain and reuse your personal data for your own purposes across different services.  It applies where the following conditions are met:

you provided the personal data to us yourself;

  * we are processing the data either based on your consent or because it is necessary for the performance of a contract; and
  * the processing is carried out by automated means.

We will provide your data free of charge in a structured, commonly used and machine readable form.  We aim to provide your data within 1 month of receiving your request unless it is particularly complicated or you have made several requests, in which case we aim to respond within 3 months.  If we are going to take longer than 1 month we will let you know and explain why we need more time.  If we consider that we cannot provide you with your data, we will contact you and explain why this is.

**Contact and complaints**

If you have any questions about this policy or about how we use your personal data please contact the Data Protection Officer at: [privacy@jet2.com.](mailto:privacy@jet2.com)

If you are unhappy about how we are processing your data or how we have responded to a request or complaint, you have the right to make a complaint to the UK's data protection regulator, the Information Commissioner's Office ( **ICO** ).  You can find more details about how to contact the ICO on their website <https://ico.org.uk/>

**Last updated: 7 February 2019**
